Lorwin, Lewis L. Papers 5152
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Lewis L. Lorwin Papers
1936-1971
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Lorwin, Lewis L.
5152
2 cubic feet
2 linear ft.
Reports.
Consist chiefly of reports and agendas of the International Confederation of Free Trade Unions, correspondence, studies and reports regarding international relations, the world economy and trade unions throughout the world, especially in postwar Europe
2293749
Biographical / Historical
Lewis Lorwin was an economist and labor historian, who over the course of his career, worked as economic advisor to the International Labor Office, the New York State Labor Department, the National Resources Planning Board, and the Foreign Economic Administration. He also held positions at the Brookings Institution and the Office of International Trade of the Department of Commerce.
Scope and Contents
Boxes 1 and 2 consist of agendas, resolutions, bulletins, and reports from the general secretary, regional organizations, and various committees of the International Confederation of Free Trade Unions (ICFTU) held in Brussels and New York, 1949-1962. Topics include nuclear warfare and universal disarmament, World Refugee Year (1959), foreign investments in economically underdeveloped countries, atomic energy, expansion of international trade, married women in employment, foreign assistance to developing countries, fair labor standards in international trade, the European coal and steel community, international migration problems, ICFTU boycott of South Africa, forced labor, plantation workers, workweek, Hungarian people's fight for freedom, the Middle East, and the United Nations. Also materials on Aden, Algeria, Aruba, Berlin, Brazil, Congo, Costa Rica, Curacao, Cyprus, Dominican Republic, Finland, Greece, Indonesia, Italy, Japan, Korea, Latin America, Lebanon, Netherlands Antilles, Nyasaland (Malawi), Oceania, Okinawa, Pakistan, Paraguay, Portugal (and the Portuguese colonies), Rhodesia, Spain, Suriname, Thailand, Tibet, Tunisia, Uganda, Venezuela, and West Irian (Dutch New Guinea).
Boxes 3 and 4 contain reprints of articles by Lorwin and clippings, news releases, speeches and published articles on the CIO and A.F. of L. abroad, socialism, and communism.
Also copies of letters (l947) from Matthew Woll (vice-president of the American Federation of Labor) to George C. Marshall (secretary of state) regarding the situation in Germany which shut the A.F.of L. off from the French and Russian zones; to Robert P. Patterson (secretary of war) regarding the A.F. of L. protest of the visit of the World Federation of Trade Unions (WFTU) mission to Japan and Korea (with Patterson's reply); to Premier Paul Ramadier regarding the French military government in Germany refusing A.F. of L. representative entry permit into French zones and refusal to accept mail.
Studies and reports concern A.F. of L. union structure (1939), communism in Eastern and Southeastern Europe (1947), trade union government (1961), labor-management relations (1960), trade union issues (1947), labor philosophy (1959), neo-institutionalism and economic change (1965), labor racketeering (1965), wage price guidelines (1966), reconstruction of the international union movement (1949), World Trade Union Conference (1944), coal economy throughout the world (1947), and Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO) (1948).
Also scattered holograph notes.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5582: Archives Foreign File (AFF) 5956: Archives Organization File Additional records
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives 227 Ives Hall Tower Road Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheelref@cornell.edu https://catherwood.library.cornell.edu/kheel/
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, September 19, 2013
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, March 07, 2019
Nuclear disarmament; Atomic power -- International control; Nuclear disarmament.; Berlin (Germany) -- Politics and government -- 1945-1990; Berlin (Germany) -- History -- 1945-1990; Boycotts -- South Africa; Communism -- Europe, Eastern; Communism -- Europe, Southern; Economic assistance, American.; Forced labor; Foreign trade and employment; International economic relations.; International labor activities; Labor policy -- Aden; Labor policy -- Cyprus; Labor policy -- Dominican Republic; Labor policy -- Greece; Labor policy -- Indonesia; Labor policy -- Korea (South); Labor policy -- Okinawa Island (Japan); Labor policy -- Paraguay; Labor policy -- Rhodesia and Nyasaland; Labor policy -- Thailand; Racketeering -- United States; Reconstruction (1939-1951) -- Europe; Refugees; Sex discrimination in employment.; Labor unions -- Africa; Labor unions -- Algeria; Labor unions -- Aruba; Labor unions -- Brazil; Labor unions -- Costa Rica; Labor unions -- Finland; Labor unions -- Italy; Labor unions -- Japan; Labor unions -- Latin America; Labor unions -- Lebanon; Labor unions -- Near East; Labor unions -- Netherlands Antilles; Labor unions -- Oceania; Labor unions -- Pakistan; Labor unions -- Portugal; Labor unions -- Surinam; Labor unions -- Tunisia; Labor unions -- Uganda; Labor unions -- Venezuela; Labor unions -- Zaire; Labor unions and communism; Economists; Coal mining -- Europe; Developing countries -- Foreign economic relations; Steel industry and trade -- Europe; Germany -- History -- Allied occupation, 1945-; Hungary -- History -- Revolution, 1956; Irian Jaya (Indonesia) -- Politics and government -- To 1963; Spain -- Politics and government -- 1939-1975; Tibet (China) -- Autonomy; Lorwin, Lewis Levitzki, 1883-1970; Marshall, George C. (George Catlett), 1880-1959; Patterson, Robert P. (Robert Porter), 1891-1952; Ramadier, Paul, 1888-1961; Woll, Matthew, 1880-1956; International Confederation of Free Trade Unions; United Nations; World Federation of Trade Unions
2293749
- ICFTU Executive Board Minutes (folder 1 of 2), 1952 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Topics include international migration, rearmament, conference of NATO experts
- ICFTU Executive Board Minutes (folder 2 of 2), 1952 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Topics include the European steel and coal community, publication/publicity, mission to Venezuela, communism in the Soviet Union, delegation to the Middle East, Tunisia
- ICFTU Final Report of Mission to Mauritius, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Marked "Confidential"
- ICFTU Executive Board Minutes (folder 1 of 4), 1955 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Topics include communism in Latin America, plantation workers, the Philippines, Indonesia, right to self-determination for Cyprus, Okinawa
- ICFTU Executive Board Minutes (folder 2 of 4), 1955 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Topics include forced labor, plantation workers, dictatorships in communist countries, oil refinery workers
- ICFTU Executive Board Minutes (folder 3 of 4), 1955 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Topics include missions to the Middle East and Colombia, equal pay, forced labor, migration, coal and steel, atomic weapons, and dictatorships and human rights
- ICFTU Executive Board Minutes (folder 4 of 4), 1955 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Includes report on mission to Rhodesia and Nyasaland
- ICFTU Executive Board Minutes (folder 1 of 3), 1956 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Topics include trade union action in Hungary and the Middle East, international films and summer schools, atomic energy, migration, the Dominican Republic, forced labor in the Soviet Union
- ICFTU Executive Board Minutes (folder 2 of 3), 1956 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Topics include Poznan protests in Poland, ILO report on forced labor, situations in Algeria, Chile, Cyprus, and the Dominican Republic
- ICFTU Executive Board Minutes (folder 3 of 3), 1956 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Topics include mission to Okinawa, Trujillo in the Dominican Republic, situations in Algeria and other countries
- ICFTU Executive Board Minutes (folder 1 of 3), 1957 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Topics include delegation to Iran, situations in Venezuela, Algeria, Hungary and others
- ICFTU Daily Bulletins and Executive Board Minutes (folder 1 of 2), 1957 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Contains daily bulletins from ICFTU 5th World Congress, reports from Joint ICFTU/ITS Consultative Committee for Women Workers' Questions, resolutions and statements from ICFTU 3rd Asian Regional Conference
- ICFTU Daily Bulletins and Executive Board Minutes (folder 2 of 2), 1957 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Contains daily bulletins from ICFTU 5th World Congress, a report from the Committee on Atomic Energy, and a report on summer schools
- ICFTU Executive Board Minutes (folder 1 of 4), 1958 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Topics include Union of South Africa, African Labour College, strikes in Spain, apartheid in the clothing industry, Finland
- ICFTU Executive Board Minutes (folder 2 of 4), 1958 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Topics include ICFTU Consultative Council, workers' education, Vietnam, North Africa, World Refugee Year, Cuba, mission to central and east Africa
- ICFTU Executive Board Minutes (folder 3 of 4), 1958 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Topics include foreign aid and investment, children's homes and young workers. Includes minutes in French.
- ICFTU Executive Board Minutes (folder 4 of 4), 1958 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Topics include WFTU 4th World Congress, missions to Japan and Venezuela, plan for African Labour Education Center, mission to Cyprus, May Day and International Solidarity Day
- ICFTU Executive Board Minutes (folder 1 of 2), 1959 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Topics include South African boycott, publications, education, women workers, Cuba, the United Nations, international trade, atomic weapons, the Tunisian General Labor Union (UGTA), General Union of Workers of Black Africa (UGTAN), World Refugee Year, May Day
- ICFTU Executive Board Minutes (folder 2 of 2), 1959 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  Topics include nuclear warfare and disarmament, youth and women, publications and education, foreign investment, atomic energy, resolutions on South Africa, Tibet, and other countries
- ICFTU Executive Board Minutes (folder 1 of 2), 1960 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  Topics include South African boycott, Korea, the UN's Freedom from Hunger campaign, and Japan
- ICFTU Executive Board Minutes (folder 2 of 2), 1960 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  Topics include Consultative Meeting on Africa, goodwill mission to Asia, fair labor standards, women workers
- ICFTU Executive Board Minutes (folder 1 of 2), 1961 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  Topics include discrimination against married women in employment, women workers, fair labor standards, and communist trade union schools
- ICFTU Executive Board Minutes (folder 2 of 2), 1961 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  Topics include mission to Greece, Portuguese colonies, FAO (Food and Agriculture Organization of the UN) Mediterranean project
- ICFTU Executive Board Minutes, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  Topics include publications/publicity and report on Japanese trade unions that includes copies of correspondence
- AFL Abroad, 1946-1947 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Communism, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Communism, 1951-1953 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- CIO Abroad, 1945-1947 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- CIO Abroad, 1947-1949 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Labor Abroad Miscellaneous, 1947-1949 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Labor and The Economic Cooperation Administration, 1948-1949 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- WFTU, 1947; 1953 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  Contains a memorandum on communism in Eastern and Southeastern Europe by Vernon VanDyke
- WFTU - Background and Organization, 1944-1947 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- WFTU Communism, 1951-1954 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- WFTU - Bulletin d'Information, 1945-1947 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- World War II and After, 1951-1954 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- ICFTU Information Bulletin, 1954-1959 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Provisonal Report of the 2nd WFTU Enquiry Commission on the Situation in Germany, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  World Federation of Trade Unions. January-February 1947
- Federation of the Coal Industry in the World, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  Report presented to the Executive Bureau, Executive Committee, and the General Council of the World Federation of Trade Unions. Prague, June 2-14, 1947.
- Columbia University Seminar on Labor, 1959-1966 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  March 17, 1965.
- Newsletters, 1957-1971 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Socialist International Information, 1951-1957 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  v.1:no.29-30 (1951: July 21). Includes correspondence from May 13, 1957
- ICFTU Constitution and other publications, 1949-1958 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Third World Trade Union Congress, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  Vienna, October 10-21, 1953.
- Reprints of Articles by Lewis L. Lorwin and his son Val R. Lorwin, 1936, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Text digitized from the collection. (Box 5)